Guide to the Fred J. Stancliff Rice University athletics records and personal papers, 1912-1990 UA 364
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Fred J. Stancliff Rice University athletics records and personal papers
1912-1990
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Stancliff, Fred J.
UA 364
1 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection consists of materials accumulated by a major alumni supporter of Rice athletics over sixty years. Included is a program from the Texas Relays in 1926 which shows the discus throwing record in the Southwest Conference held by the creator of the collection. There are programs from a few other particular events, but most of the collection relates to the R Association, of which Stancliff was secretary-treasurer for over sixty years. There are membership lists, correspondence with specific supporters, records of travel costs, information about fund-raising activities, and memorabilia from the 1930's through the 1970's.
Biographical / Historical
Fred J. Stancliff for 63 years was the secretary-treasurer of the Rice University organization for all athletes whose participation earned them the award of the letter R. He and his wife Florence are credited with keeping the R Association operating through decades of Rice athletics that are referred to as "The Stancliff Years."
Stancliff came to Rice from El Campo, Texas, and as a freshman was captain of the track team. He distinguished himself particularly as a discus thrower. Attention to his expertise was drawn not only by distance records but also by a photograph showing him in position ready to throw. The resemblance of the photograph to a well- known Greek statue led to its being printed first in the rotogravure section of a Houston newspaper and then circulated nationally.
Stancliff was elected secretary of the R Association in 1923 when he accepted his first varsity letter. He continued in that position and added treasurer to it, serving until 1986. In 1971 the organization honored him with the Distinguished R Man Award, and in 1973 he was recognized with a tribute as "the man who has been the motivating and sustaining force in our organization for the last 50 years."
A Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering is the degree Stancliff earned, graduating in 1926. Until the Depression years he worked as a field and petroleum engineer. Friendship with a fellow alumnus who had been captain of the football team led to his being offered a job selling insurance for Southland Life. By 1935 he was given the opportunity to become a general agent for Volunteer State Life Insurance Company, a position he held for many years.
Sancliff died in 1995.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials accumulated by a major alumni supporter of Rice athletics over sixty years. Many of the items involve the R Association, the organization to which all varsity athletes can belong. There are correspondence files about dues, yearly banquets, and other activities. Included is the R Association roster from 1912 to 1952. There are membership lists of the R Association Hall of Fame, the Quarterback Club (1998, 2004), and the Student Owl Club (2004-05). Also included are the R Association by-laws and the certificate form for an R Association Honorary Member.
In addition to the R Association items, there are materials about various projects to raise funds for athletics, e.g. a 1998 Phone-a-thon, baseball Dollars for Dingers (2004), the baseball commemorative brick campaign (2007), and For Rice's Honor programs. Records of the budget, fund raising, and insurance of the Owl Club are also included.
Widely ranging particular events are represented, such as Homecoming 1954, Rice Day 1959, Letterman's Day 1997, the reunion of 1930 to 1939 football players in 1998, the Association of Rice Alumni Pre-Game Parties in 1999, an Owl Club retreat in 2000, Red Bale dinners, a San Antonio Athletics Alumni Reception in 2006, the Blue and Gray Weekend in 2006, and Rodeo Nights in 1997, 1998, and 2001.
Programs from specific events include Track and Field Programs from 1925-26, the 1950's, 1962, and 1974; the 2000 Baseball Schedule; and the 1970 Southwest Conference Championship. There are copies of an athletics newsletter titled Talon, as well as random newsclips.
Finally, the collection includes envelopes of memorabilia from the 1930's 1940's, 1950's, 1960's and 1970's. There are some of Stancliff's personal letters, as well as his honors and awards from the R Association. A folder marked "Rice Stadium" contains diagrams and information about the financing dated 1951.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Athletics Department, Summer of 2015.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Sports
Document Types
letters (correspondence); programs (documents); memorabilia; notes
Subjects (Persons)
Stancliff, Fred J.
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University; Rice University. "R" Association
- Series I: Operational (Box 1)
  - 'R' Association Hall of Fame (Box 1)
    - 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clubs (Box 1)
    - Quarterback Club (Box 1)
      - 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Student Owl Club, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Owl Club (Box 1)
      - Policy and procedures manual, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - R Association by-laws, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - R Association alumni roster, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Owls Nest tent, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Baseball rings, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Baseball schedule, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Women's golf planning, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Travel (Box 1)
    - Brochure for Traveling Owls, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Air Force, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brigham Young, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - New Mexico, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Northwestern, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - SMU, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Texas, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - TCU, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Tulane, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Tulsa, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Utah, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - UTEP, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Football travel, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Parking (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Volunteer meeting, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Contact reports (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series II: Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1920s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1940s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1950s (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1960s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 1970s (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Proposal letters, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Donor letters, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Larry Brune (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Charles Duncan (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Robert Estill (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Jim Gasso (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Roy Goodearle (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Matt Gorges (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Craig Hermann (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Brad Hovius (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Robert Ley (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Bobby May (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Ken Simmons (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Series III: Financial (Box 1)
  - Owl Club (Box 1)
    - Owl Club budget, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Owl Club fundraising plan, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Owl Club insurance, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Baseball commemorative brick campaign, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Donor survey (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - 'R' Association dues, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Track, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Phon-a-thon, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Major donors (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Major donor weekend, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Solicitation letter, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Baseball "Dollars for Dingers", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Laura Wharton estate, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Charles & Anne Straub Scholarship Fund, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - DePelchin's Children's Center grant proposals, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Series IV: Events (Box 1)
  - Homecoming, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Rice Day, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Graduate Research Addition to Fondren Library, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Rice Athletic Hall of Fame & Distinguished R Man Award, 1970-1985 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Emmett E. Brunson appreciation, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Letterman's Day, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Hall of Fame ceremonies, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Football recruiting party, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - George Strait concert, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - "R" reunion, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - An Evening for Rice's Honor, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - 1930-39 football teams reunion, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Red Bale reunion, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Association of Rice Alumni pre-game parties, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Owl Club retreat, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Red Bale dinner, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - San Antonio athletics alumni reception, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Blue & Gray Weekend, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Rodeo Night, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Rodeo Night, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Rodeo Night, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Series V: Publications (Box 1)
  - Track & Field programs, 1955-1974 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Talon, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Football event-related (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Southwest Conference Championships program, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - 'R' Association roster, 1912-1952 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Owl Band of Rice University, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - 'R' Association Honorary Member certificate/form (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Newsclips (Box 1, Folder 92)
- Series VI: Memorabilia (Box 1)
  - 1930s (Box 1, Envelope 93)
  - 1940s (Box 1, Envelope 94)
  - 1950s (Box 1, Envelope 95)
  - 1960s (Box 1, Envelope 96)
  - 1970s (Box 1, Envelope 97)
- Series VII: Personal
  - Correspondence
    - Oren Arnold (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Max Roensch (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Family (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Honors and awards (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Rice Stadium (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Newsclips
    - Family (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Fred J. (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Friends (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Track programs, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 102)